<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glass for religious princes, or, The character and work of Josiah delivered in a sermon upon 2 Kings XXIII.XXV : the substance whereof was preached April 5 1691 at Pershore in Worcester-shire ... / by Richard Claridge ...</title>
            <author>Claridge, Richard, 1649-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33247</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2252</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12015148</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12015148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52511</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33247)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52511)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 886:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glass for religious princes, or, The character and work of Josiah delivered in a sermon upon 2 Kings XXIII.XXV : the substance whereof was preached April 5 1691 at Pershore in Worcester-shire ... / by Richard Claridge ...</title>
                  <author>Claridge, Richard, 1649-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author :</publisher>
                  <publisher>and are to be sold by William Marshall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Kings, 2nd, XXIII, 25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52511:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52511:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LOOKING-GLASS FOR Religious Princes: OR, THE CHARACTER AND WORK of JOSIAH, Delivered in a SERMON UPON 2 KINGS XXIII.XXV. The Subſtance whereof was Preached April 5. 1691. at Perſhore in Worceſter-ſhire.</p>
            <p>Wherein They may ſee,
<list>
                  <item>That thoſe Princes are only Eminent in the Sight of God, who are truly Religious, and turn to the Lord with all their Heart.</item>
                  <item>That there is more required of ſuch Princes, than their own Private Aſſent and Conſent to the True Religion.</item>
                  <item>That Religious Princes cannot be capable of a greater Honour in this World, than to be the Inſtruments of a Godly Reformation among their Subjects.</item>
                  <item>And, That the Word of God alone is the Rule, to which both they and their People muſt attend in all Matters relating to Religion</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By RICHARD CLARIDGE, M. A. and then Rector of Peopleton in the County of Worceſter.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold by William Marſhall at the Bible in Newgate-ſtreet, 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:52511:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:52511:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LOOKING GLASS FOR Religious Princes, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 KINGS XXIII. 25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And like unto him was there no King before him, that turned to the Lord with all his Heart, and with all his Soul, and with all his Might, according to all the Law of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, neither after him aroſe there any like him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>OF all the Publick Bleſſings that Almighty God is pleaſed to beſtow upon Nations as Nations, or Bodies Politick, there cannot be conceived a greater than good and wholſome Laws, Agreed upon and Enacted for the benefit and Emolument of the whole Society, and godly and upright Governours to put thoſe Laws in Execution. For, as it is natural for men to enter into Society, Man not being <hi>Animal monaſticum, ſed politicum,</hi> a Monkiſh but ſociable Creature; ſo it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Agree upon Laws for the preſervation of it. And foraſmuch as the main deſign of all Laws and Government ſhould be <hi>Gloria Dei, &amp; ſalus Populi,</hi> the Glory of God, and the Weal and Safety of the State; thoſe Laws are ever
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52511:3"/> beſt which have the directeſt tendency to thoſe Ends: but ſeeing alſo that the beſt Laws are uſeleſs, and inſufficient for the attaining of thoſe Ends, unleſs executed according to the true intent and meaning of them, and this cannot be done but by Governours intruſted with the Adminiſtration thereof; and becauſe it often happens that the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Affairs falls into ill hands, who offend either through Remiſsneſs, Rigour, or Arbitrarineſs; and thereby Ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate or Debauch the People; or ſo Oppreſs them by Illegal Exactions,<note place="margin">Mic. 3.1, 2.</note> that like the <hi>Princes of Iſrael, they pluck their skin from off them, and their fleſh from off their bones:</hi> It is therefore a ſingular Inſtance of a benign Providence to a People, when a skillful and religious Pilot is placed at the Rudder of the Government; who will take care for the Enacting and Executing of good Laws, always obſerving a due diſtance between the two Extreams, Softneſs and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, into one of which moſt Princes both of later and former days have fall'n. It is the happineſs of <hi>England,</hi> could ſhe ſee her happineſs, that ſhe is delivered from <hi>One</hi> who trampled upon all Laws, and by vertue of an Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Diſpenſing Power did what he liſted; and has a <hi>moſt Excellent Prince</hi> placed at the Stern, whoſe Head the Lord cover in the day of Battel, and appoint unto him Salvation for Walls and Bulwarks. Under his Conduct the Ship of the Commonwealth is likely to ſail ſecurely, even among Rocks and Shelves: ſuch Princes are the Favourites of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, God will take them and make them as Signets, and put them as choice Shafts in the Quiver of his ſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. In their day the Government ſhall triumph, it ſhall bid defiance to Treachery at Home, and Oppoſition from Abroad, for the Lord of Hoſts is with them, the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> is their Refuge.</p>
            <p>When the Government is Adminiſtred by a Pious, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and upright Prince, who hath nothing equal in his Proſpect to the Honour of God, and the Common Welfare; there the People are out of danger of Oppreſſion and Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ſhall <hi>dwell ſafely, every man under his Vine, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52511:3"/> his Fig-tree,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 4.25.</note> as <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> did in the days of <hi>Solomon.</hi> Now of thoſe two, the Honour of God, and the Common Welfare, the preference muſt be always given to the firſt;<note place="margin">Mat. 22.37, 38. Deut. 6.5.</note> becauſe <hi>this is the firſt and great Commandment, Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, and with all thy mind.</hi> The Precept reaches Princes as well as People, and it ſhould be the chief care of Governours to obſerve it:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For tho' they are ſometimes called <hi>Gods</hi> in Scripture, yet they are but earthly ones,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and <hi>by way of Similitude,</hi> as <hi>Agapetus</hi> told <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould ever remember themſelves to be the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the <hi>Moſt High.</hi> There is all the reaſon in the World that Gods Honour ſhould be firſt regarded by Princes in their Dominions, becauſe <hi>the Moſt High ruleth in the Kingdom of men;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4.17. &amp; 5.21.2.21.</note> 
               <hi>and appointeth over it whomſoever he will;</hi> for <hi>he changeth the times and the ſeaſons, he removeth Kings, and ſetteth up Kings:</hi> and becauſe the Happineſs of a Nation depends upon its relation to the King of Kings.</p>
            <p>It is the obſervation of Wiſe and Experienc'd <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> that <hi>Righteouſneſs exalteth a Nation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 14 34.</note> 
               <hi>but ſin is a reproach to any people.</hi> I ſhall not here enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> is to be reſtrained to Moral Juſtice, or to be taken in a more comprehenſive ſenſe for Religion and Vertue in general. Experience can atteſt, that Piety and Morality have a Mighty Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the Proſperity of a Nation, and that Vice and Wickedneſs have been always fatal in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences to it.</p>
            <p>Religion is the beſt Cement of Society, and binds men in the ſtricteſt obligations to be Juſt, and True, and Honeſt to one another: For where Religion is truly embraced, it has its Tye upon the Conſcience,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52511:4"/> and that by a powerful Energy checks and commands the whole Man: for Conſcience, I mean, the enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened and ſanctified Conſcience, will be always doing its office, in Accuſing or Excuſing; and he that hath ſuch a Monitor, muſt be prodigiouſly inadvertent, if he do not perceive its Motions, and attend to them.</p>
            <p>On the other hand, where Vice is grown predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and become the Epidemical diſtemper of a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, there the Bond of Conſcience is diſſolv'd, becauſe their Union with God is broken. And when that Bond is diſſolv'd, the People are under no Tye, but that of Humane Laws; and how weak Humane Laws are of themſelves to make a Nation truly happy, is ſadly apparent, from the many woful diſtreſſes the Nations are under at this day, by reaſon of their Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy from God.</p>
            <p>'Tis natural for men to lay the blame of all their Miſeries upon miſtaken Cauſes, and to make thoſe Perſons and Things the Authors of their Calamities, which really are not. Thus wicked <hi>Ahab</hi> charged the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> with being the cauſe of the ſore Famine in <hi>Samaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 4.25. 1 Kings 18.17.</note> 
               <hi>when the Heaven was ſhut up three years and ſix months,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Art thou he that troubleth Iſrael?</hi> Thus the innocent Apoſtles were accuſed for being Diſturbers of the Publick Peace,<note place="margin">Acts 17.6.</note> and <hi>Turners of the World upſide down. Paul</hi> was impleaded by <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> for a <hi>peſtilent fellow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ch. 24.5.</note> and <hi>a mover of Sedition.</hi> And the Primitive Chriſtians were traduced by the Heathen Perſecutors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertul. Apol.</hi> c. 37. p. 30.</note> as the <hi>Peſts and Enemies of Mankind,</hi> and that they and their Doctrine procured all the Evils that ſo frequently befell the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. Hence aroſe that general outcry againſt the Chriſtians in thoſe days,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr. Ep. ad Demetr.</hi> p. 197. <hi>Arnob. adv.</hi> gen. l. 1. p. 1.</note> when any misfortune happened, <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos ad Leones,</hi> Away with the Chriſtians to the Lions. For 'twas the Common Objection upon every occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52511:4"/> that <hi>they were the Authors of all publick Calamities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as then they who were <hi>born after the Fleſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted</hi> them who were <hi>born after the Spirit,</hi> even ſo it has been of <hi>late</hi> among us, and would ('tis to be fear'd) be ſo <hi>now,</hi> had ſome Men the Power they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had. Do not they object the diſtreſſes of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Age, to the Pious and Sober People of the Nation, as if they were the Procurers of their Misfortunes, and the Troublers of their <hi>Iſrael?</hi> How often do we hear it urg'd, That <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are worſe than <hi>Papiſts?</hi> that 'twill never be well in <hi>England</hi> ſo long as the <hi>Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> ſtands? and that <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> is <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um malorum Fons,</hi> the Fountain of all Miſchiefs?</p>
            <p>But alas, poor Envious and miſtaken Wretches! <hi>Whom do they reproach and blaſpheme? and againſt whom do they exalt their voice, and lift up their eyes on high?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 37.23.</note> 
               <hi>even againſt the Holy One of Iſrael.</hi> In compaſſion to their Souls, I could wiſh they knew what ſpirit they were of, and were convinced how contrary a Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Temper is to the Example and Precepts of our Saviour and his Apoſtles, and to the whole Genius, Scope and Deſign of the Goſpel. Let them read the Scripture, and ſhew me where Perſecution is taught in Terms or Conſequence, and I will believe it then to be lawful to Plunder and Impriſon my Neighbour, yea, to execute the Writ <hi>de Haeretico comburendo.</hi> But till it be proved from Scripture, that I may lawfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute my Neighbour purely for Religion, and becauſe he judges of Spiritual things otherwiſe than I do; I will always believe a Perſecuting Spirit to be Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and as oppoſite to the Goſpel as Darkneſs is to Light, and Papal Cruelty to Apoſtolical Meekneſs.</p>
            <p>To correct theſe Mens Miſtakes, is to ſhew them the true Cauſe of all their Troubles, by reſolving them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their proper Originals, their Sins and Apoſtacies from God. Thus <hi>Elijah</hi> told <hi>Ahab, I have not troubled Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 18.18.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52511:5"/> 
               <hi>but thou and thy Fathers Houſe, in that ye have forſaken the Commandments of the Lord, and thou haſt followed Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim.</hi> And the ancient Apologiſts, <hi>Tertullian, Cyprian, Arnobius,</hi> and others, took this as the moſt ſucceſsful courſe to ſtop the ſlanderous mouths of their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. The Heathen charg'd the Chriſtians with their publick Misfortunes; the Chriſtians cleared themſelves from thoſe Aſperſions, and ſhew'd their Adverſaries how to reſolve their Evils into their true Cauſes, ſuch as Idolatry, Debauchery, and Ingratitude, the crimes not only of the ancient <hi>Pagans,</hi> but of too many Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Profeſſors of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ask perhaps, Is it not a contradiction to ſay, <hi>Chriſtian Idolaters?</hi> I anſwer, No, becauſe there are a great many ſuch in the World. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> are groſs Idolaters, for to worſhip God <hi>by, in,</hi> or <hi>thrô</hi> any Image or Similitude of Saint or Angel, as they do, is groſs Idolatry. A late Popiſh Author endeavours to excuſe this practice;<note n="*" place="margin">A Papiſt miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repr. and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented. <hi>p.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>All the Veneration,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that the Papiſt expreſſes before Images, whether by kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, praying, lifting up the eyes, burning Candles, Incenſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>'tis not at all done for the Image, but is wholly reſerv'd to the thing repreſented, which he intends to honour by theſe actions.</hi> But this will not do, unleſs he could perſwade us, the Religious uſe of Images were enjoyned in the Second Commandment, and all his ſuperſtitious Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms allow'd by it; which will never be, ſo long as we have our Bibles, and ſee all Image-worſhip expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbidden therein.</p>
            <p>There is alſo another ſort of Idolaters, who are more refined than the bigotted <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and yet are no leſs guilty in the ſight of God than they. Now the Idolatry of theſe men conſiſts in <q rend="margQuotes">Performing that unto the True God, which hath a Similitue, Show and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of his Service, but is not ſo indeed; becauſe he<note n="(a)" place="margin">Deut. 12.32</note> requireth it not at our hands, and therefore is but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52511:5"/> a<note n="(b)" place="margin">Col. 2.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Will-worſhip,</hi> or voluntary Religion, a thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed and done<note n="(c)" place="margin">Hoſ. 13.2.</note> 
                  <hi>according to our own underſtanding.</hi>
               </q> See <hi>Ainſworth</hi>'s Arrow againſt Idolatry, <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 3, 4.</p>
            <p>It were well, if the Church of <hi>England</hi> could clear her ſelf of this kind of Idolatry; ſhe knows the Diſſenters charge has been often drawn up againſt her, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by a Cloud of Witneſſes. And if ſhe can make no better defence than hitherto ſhe hath made, it will be both her Wiſdom and Honour to acknowledge her Guilt, and return unto God by Repentance and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">The ſecond Commandment, ſaith the<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Arrow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Idol.</hi> c. 1. p. 4, 5. Joh. 4.20.—24.</note> excellent <hi>Ainſworth,</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Deu. 12.32. &amp; 4.1, 2, 5, 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> bindeth to the true worſhip of the true God, which is only<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.113. Iſa. 29.13. Col 2.23. &amp; 22.</note> as himſelf commandeth, and by the Means, Rites and Services that he ordaineth; and it forbiddeth
<list>
                     <item>1. All Inventions of our own to worſhip God by, voluntary Religion, Opinions and Doctrines of men.</item>
                     <item>2. All Imitations of<note n="(g)" place="margin">Lev. 18.2, 3. Deut. 12.30.31. Rev. 17.2.</note> Heathens or Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in their God ſervices, to do the like unto the Lord our God.</item>
                     <item>3. All Imitation or Counterfeiting<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Kings 12.28.32. Amos 4.4, 5. &amp; 5.21.22, 23. Hoſ. 8.14.</note> of Gods own Ordinances and Inſtitutions, as to make Temples like his Temple, Feaſts like his Feaſts, Altars like his, Miniſters like his, which was the Sin of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. All neglect of Gods Services, or of the Means and Inſtruments by him ordained; all irreligious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs or hypocriſie; together with all communion with ſuch kind of Idolatry, all cauſes, occaſions, and provocation thereunto.</item>
                  </list>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now when a Nation is overrun with Idolatry and other ſorts of Wickedneſs, to the great Diſhonour of God, and ſcandal of good Men; it is the Buſineſs of Religious Princes to endeavour to retrieve the Honour of God, and ſatisfie pious Minds, by a general Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Idolatry and Vice, becauſe as they reign
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52511:6"/> 
               <hi>by him,</hi> ſo they ſhould reign <hi>for him</hi> too. God puts the Crown upon their Heads, and Scepter into their Hands, for other purpoſes, than to ſuffer<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Kings 12 28. Micah 6.16.</note> 
               <hi>Jeroboams Calves, Omri's Statutes,</hi> and <hi>the Works of the Houſe of Ahab.</hi> He exalts them to Soveraign Dignity for more excellent Ends: They ſhould always have his Glory in their Eye, and poſtpone all other Ends to that. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have an Example of a King the moſt illuſtrious Scripture Hiſtory affords, and who hath left a Copy of Extraordinary Zeal for God to all ſucceeding Kings to write after, 'tis <hi>Joſiah</hi> King of <hi>Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And like unto him was there no King before him, that turn'd to the Lord with all his heart,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Text contains the Character and Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> with the Work and Duty of his Day, and in him preſents us with a Looking-Glaſs for Chriſtian Princes: Or 'tis a compleat Idea, and exact Deſcription of a truly Religious King, <hi>He turned to the Lord with all his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Joſiah</hi> came to the Crown, he found the Kingdom univerſally polluted with Idolatry, both Prieſts and People were infected, and every Age and Sex (a Remnant excepted) had corrupted their ways: His Great Grandfather <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was a very good King, and had deſtroyed all publick Idolatry in the Land;<note n="*" place="margin">2 Kings 18.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>He removed the high places, and brake the Images, and cut down the Groves, and brake in pieces the brazen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent that Moſes had made:</hi> (becauſe it was abuſed to Idolatry,) <hi>for unto thoſe days the Children of Iſrael burnt Incenſe to it. He truſted in the Lord God of Iſrael, ſo that after him was none like him, among all the Kings of Judah, nor any that were before him:</hi> But in the Reigns of his Grandfather <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and Father <hi>Amon,</hi> whoſe Hiſtory is ſet down 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry increaſed like <hi>Hydra</hi>'s heads, and the worſhip of <hi>Baalim,</hi> or Idols of the Sun, prevailed over the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52511:6"/> of the True God. For<note n="(i)" place="margin">2 King. 21.3.</note> 
               <hi>Manaſſeh built up again the High Places which his Father Hezekiah had deſtroyed, and he reared up Altars for Baal, and made a Grove, as did Ahab, and worſhipped all the Hoſt of Heaven, and ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.</hi> And if we look into the<note n="(k)" place="margin">Regnavit Annis <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ſhort Reign of his Son <hi>Amon,</hi> we ſhall find he was no better than his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but ſucceeded him in his Throne and Impieties together: For<note n="(l)" place="margin">2 Kings 21, 20.</note> 
               <hi>he did that which was evil in the ſight of the Lord, as his Father Manaſſeh did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> as wicked a King as he had been, after his Repentance<note n="(n)" place="margin">2 Chron. 33.12,—16.6. v. 17.</note> did pretty conſiderably toward a Reformation;<note n="(o)" place="margin">2 Chron. 29.3.</note> 
               <hi>Nevertheleſs the People did ſacrifice ſtill in the High Places.</hi> But in <hi>Amons</hi> time the Reformation was utterly quaſht, till the Reign of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> in whoſe time it was carried on with wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full zeal and ſucceſs. For <hi>like unto him was there no King before him, neither after him aroſe any like him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how can this be, when the ſame Character is given of <hi>Hezekiah?</hi> For 'tis ſaid 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.5. <hi>After him was none like him, among all the Kings of Judah, nor any that were before him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For reſolution of this Queſtion, ſeveral things may be offered in Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It muſt be underſtood with Exception of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> becauſe this Commendation is likewiſe given to him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Phraſe denotes them both to have <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> been eminently Religious.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They had their particular Excellencies, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> wherein they both outſtript. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſhew'd his zeal for the true Religion at his very Acceſſion to the Throne:<note n="(p)" place="margin">2 Chron. 29 3.</note> 
               <hi>In the firſt year of his Reign, in the firſt Month, he opened the doors of the houſe of the Lord, and repaired them.</hi> For his Father <hi>Ahaz</hi> being diſtreſſed by <hi>Tig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lath-Pileſer</hi> King of <hi>Aſſyria, ſacrificed to the Gods of Damaſcus,</hi> in expectation of help from them, and <hi>ſhut
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52511:7"/> up the doors of the Temple,</hi> 2 Chron. 28.22, 23, 24. <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> being a Minor of eight years old when he came to the Crown, had no ſooner attained to the ſixteenth year of his age, moſt commonly the time of Sport and Dalliance to many other Princes; but while he was yet (thus) <hi>young,</hi> he began to ſeek after the God of <hi>David</hi> his Father.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, The Expreſſion is Hyperbolical, and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified thus,<note place="margin">Vix eis, par, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> they <hi>ſcarcely have been,</hi> or <hi>ſhall be</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall'd.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Their Zeal was equally fervent in reſtoring the pure Worſhip of God; but <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Reformation was more extenſive than <hi>Hezekiah's;</hi> for <hi>Joſiah</hi> refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med<note n="(q)" place="margin">Non in ſuo ſolum, ſed etiam in alieno regno. <hi>Sanctius</hi> ſup. <hi>2 Reg. 23.25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>not in the Kingdom of Judah only, but in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael too.</hi> When therefore we read that <hi>Hezekiah</hi> threw down the High places, and the Altars, not only out of all<note n="(r)" place="margin">2 Chr. 31.1</note> 
               <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> but in <hi>Ephraim</hi> alſo and <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> which two Tribes were part of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> It is to be underſtood with reſtriction to that<note n="(s)" place="margin">Jun. ſup. loc. <hi>Grot. ibid.</hi>
               </note> part of thoſe Tribes, which was ſubject to the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> either by Conqueſt, or a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary ſubmiſſion by reaſon of the preſent troubles of that Kingdom. But <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Reformation extended <hi>to the Altar at</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">2 Reg. 23.15.</note> 
               <hi>Bethel, and all the</hi>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">v. 19.</note> 
               <hi>houſes alſo of the high Places that were in the Cities of Samaria, which the Kings of Iſrael made to provoke the Lord to anger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, There are two things peculiar in <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Caſe, in regard of which the precedency may well be given him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He was propheſied of above<note n="(w)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Poſt annos circiter trecen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos,</hi> Jun. ſup. 1 Reg. 13.2.</note> 
               <hi>three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years,</hi> before he was born, and mention'd expreſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by name, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Joſiah;</hi> and which is very remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, it was preſently after <hi>Jeroboam</hi> had deviſed his Calf worſhip in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel;</hi> for as he <hi>ſtood by his new Altar in Bethel to burn Incenſe, behold there came
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52511:7"/> a man of God out of Judah, by the Word of the Lord, and cry'd againſt the Altar in the Word of the Lord, and ſaid, O Altar, Altar, thus ſaith the Lord; Behold</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">Heb <hi>Son.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>[a Child] ſhall be born unto the houſe of David, Joſiah by Name, and upon thee ſhall he offer the Prieſts of the High Places, that burn Incenſe upon thee, and mens bones ſhall be burnt upon thee,</hi> 1 Kings 13.1, 2. Where Obſerve, that God's jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie of his own Honour, and Love to his own Worſhip is ſuch, that he cannot endure to be rival'd by Man; but immediately proteſts againſt Falſe Worſhip and Falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers by his Servants; and thô he bears with them both for a Seaſon, yet there is a Time, ſecret to us, but fixt in God's Eternal Decree, wherein both ſhall be deſtroyed. Thus he dealt with <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Altar, and the Prieſts of the High Places, and the like deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may all others dread, who are involved in the like guilt.</p>
            <p>To ballance this Inſtance, 'tis urg'd, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> Propheſied of <hi>Cyrus</hi> (an Heathen Monarch) by Name, long before his Nativity; for according to <hi>Junius,</hi> from the time of the Prophecy, to the fulfilling of it, were 170 Years, or after <hi>Grotius</hi> 210, and therefore the Prediction of <hi>Joſiah</hi> is not ſingular.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, their Caſe was very different; <hi>Cyrus</hi> was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, as a Paſſive Inſtrument, to bring about the deſign of God's Providence in the Reſtauration of the <hi>Jews</hi> from their Babyloniſh Captivity, and giving them Liberty to Re-ediſie the Temple. <hi>Joſiah,</hi> as an Active Inſtrument, to accompliſh God's Pleaſure in the Extirpation of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael. Cyrus</hi> did the Will of God, but 'twas without any ſincere Affection to, or Religious Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God; for God ſays twice to him,<note place="margin">Iſa. 45.4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt not known me. Joſiah</hi> perform'd the Will of God, in Faith, Love and Obedience to him; <hi>He turned to the Lord with all his heart, and with all his ſoul, and with all his might.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:52511:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Another thing extraordinary in <hi>Joſiah</hi> was his moſt exact Conformity to the Divine Law, in purging his Kingdom of Idolatry.<note place="margin">2 Chron. 31.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>Hezekiah wrought that which was good, and right, and truth before the Lord his God; and in every work that he began in the ſervice of the houſe of God, and in the Law, and in the Commandments, to ſeek his God, he did it with all his heart.</hi> This is an ample Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, but <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s is ſomewhat fuller, <hi>For he turned to the Lord, with all his heart, and with all his ſoul, and with all his might, according to all the Law of Moſes.</hi> His Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion was Univerſal, <hi>for he did all according to all the Law of Moſes.</hi> His Father and his Grandfather turn'd from the Lord and his Law; but he made the Law of God his Counſellor; <hi>He ſought to the God of David his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and declined neither to the right hand, nor the left,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.2, 3. He Conſulted not with a Carnal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and a ſenſual <hi>Sanhedrim;</hi> but he ſent to <hi>Huldah</hi> the Propheteſs for Direction.</p>
            <p>Many Princes will Reform a Little, as <hi>Afa, Jehoſaphat, Joaſh, Amaziah,</hi> who were good Kings, ſo far as they did Reform; but the Blot that is upon their Names, is, the High Places were not taken away, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.14. &amp; 22.43. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.3. &amp; 14.4. Now <hi>Joſiah</hi> pull'd down theſe High Places, he left not one of them remaining. Indeed, notwithſtanding all he did or could do; Idolatry was ſo riveted in many of the Princes, Prieſts and People, that <hi>Baal had a remnant among them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jeph. 1.4.</note> for he had his <hi>Chemarims,</hi> his profeſs'd Prieſts, and he had others too, who pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be Prieſts of the True God, but would be now and then tampering with <hi>Baal</hi>'s Idolatrous Rites. They durſt not exerciſe their Idolatry publickly, for ſear of the King; but <hi>they Worſhip'd the Hoſt of Heaven on the houſe tops, and ſwore by the Lord and Malchom;</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 5.</note> they mingled true and falſe Worſhip together.</p>
            <p>And becauſe there is often mention in Scripture of theſe High Places, and the pulling of them down is recorded as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52511:8"/> an High Act of Reformation, we will enquire what they were; and this will not be loſs of time, becauſe the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> had their High Places as well as the <hi>Jews.</hi> The High Places then <hi>Heb.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sept.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, were Altars erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Hills, upon which they offered Sacrifices, the <hi>Heathen</hi> to their Idols, and the <hi>Jews</hi> to the True God. For after the Tabernacle and Ark were removed from <hi>Shiloh,</hi> which was in the dayes of <hi>Eli,</hi> when the Ark was taken, and his two Sons, <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phinehas</hi> were ſlain by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 4.3, 4, 11. The <hi>Jews</hi> uſed the High Places as moſt proper and convenient for their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; thus <hi>Samuel</hi> and the People ſacrificed in the High Place, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.12.19. and ſo it continued 'till <hi>David</hi> brought the Ark to<note n="†" place="margin">2 Chron. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and then it became the People's Duty to Sacrifice where the Ark was. And hence we read that <hi>Solomon,</hi> when the<note n="*" place="margin">V. 3.</note> Tabernacle was at <hi>Gibeon,</hi> and the Ark at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſacrificing in the High Places, and eſpecially at the great High Place in <hi>Gibeon,</hi> where thô the Lord appeared to him in a Dream by Night, yet hath this Note of Irregularity put upon him, <hi>Solomon loved the Lord, walking in the Statutes of David his Father: only he ſacrificed and burnt incenſe in the High Places. And the King went to Gibeon to ſacrifice there; for that was the Great High Place,</hi> 1 Kings 3.3, 4. After the Temple was built, and the Ark placed in it, the People were to bring their Sacrifices thither, according to that in <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.13, 14. <hi>Take heed to thy ſelf, that thou offer not thy burnt-offerings in every place that thou ſeeſt; but in the place which the Lord ſhall chuſe in one of thy Tribes, there thou ſhalt offer thy burnt-offerings, and there thou ſhalt do all that I command thee.</hi> It was the People's ſin to Sacrifice any where elſe, but at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi> thô they Sacrificed to the True God: His poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Command made that to be Sin which was not ſin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. When he had placed his Name at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and pitch'd his Tabernacle there, thither the People were bound to bring all their Offerings. But, alas! they ſoon forſook the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and return'd to their High Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52511:9"/> where not content to Worſhip the True God, thô even that Worſhip perform'd there now was ſinful, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe uncommanded; they fell to Worſhipping of <hi>Baal</hi> or the Sun, and other Idols of the Nations, which Worſhip, notwithſtanding they pretended it was for the Honour of the True God, is every where condemned for abominable Idolatry.</p>
            <p>Men may not intermeddle in the Worſhip of God to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute or alter according to their Fancies. I know they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to excuſe their Innovations, as <hi>Aaron</hi> did his Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calf, <hi>who made proclamation, and ſaid, To morrow is a Feaſt to the Lord,</hi> Exod. 32.5. Not a Feaſt to the Calf; they think Religion too plain of it ſelf, and therefore they will ſet it out in a more pompous Garb of their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing; which is very apt to take with Carnal Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: But is not acceptable with God, becauſe he approves of none, no not that which Men call <hi>Divine Service,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe but of Humane Contrivance, and neither in reſpect of Matter, Manner, or End ſuch as is preſcribed in the Word. <hi>Jeroboam</hi> had invented a notable Semblance of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, and made it look as like that of God's own appointing at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> as might be: But was God to be found in that Calfiſh Worſhip? Surely No. And as he was not to be met with there, ſo may we deſpair to find him in that Theatrical Worſhip, which he hath not Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and wherewith the Ignorant World is cajol'd at this day.</p>
            <p>There is a natural Inclination in Men to be mixing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their own with the holy Appointments of God; it is a Vice as old as the Fall, and therefore might plead Preſcription, were Antiquity in this matter a good Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Neither is there only a Natural Inclination, but ſome Perſons are poſſeſſed with ſuch a mighty Fondneſs for Additions, which Cuſtom or Inrereſt hath decoy'd them into, that they cannot think God well-Worſhipt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſinful Pageantry of their Ceremonious Decency and Order; two Words of large Extent, which when Witty
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52511:9"/> and Deſigning Men have the Explication of, they will be ſure to expound to ſuch a Latitude, as ſhall ſerve their Ends upon every occaſion.</p>
            <p>'Tis not to be queſtion'd, but that the Idolatrous Prieſts had a great deal to ſay for their Idols and High Places; they had the Examples of ſeveral Kings, the approbation of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and People, their Idols were only Symbols or Medium's through which their Worſhip paſs'd to the Supream Being, and they could tell the People they uſed them meerly for Decency and Order, and their High Places for greater Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of Devotion; for they look'd upon both Idols and High Places not as having any Divinity or Holineſs in themſelves, but as things in their own Nature indifferent; and yet being enjoyn'd, as not to be omitted, becauſe the Magiſtrate's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand changes the very Nature of things, and makes that which antecedent to his Sanction was indifferent, become immediately after to be Neceſſary, that is, Neceſſary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Commanded by the Magiſtrate. This alſo is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Plea, which has been enforc'd with all the Wit and Power of Man, to defend his Innovations in the Worſhip of God. But all his Attempts will not do, for weak ſinful Man is not able to ſtand out againſt the Omnipotent and moſt Holy God, who will maintain his Cauſe againſt all Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and make his Truth to triumph over Errour, thô back'd with the utmoſt Skill and power of Men.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Joſiah,</hi> that moſt eminent Reformer in his day; his Zeal for God manifeſted it ſelf in ſundry parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars:</p>
            <p>Firſt, He took care about the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> was much dilapidated through the Neglect of his Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Predeceſſors,<note place="margin">2 King. 22.3.4, 5.</note> and gave <hi>Hilkiah</hi> Orders to <hi>repair the Breaches thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, As ſoon as the Book of the Law was found, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and read before him, and he heard the Wrath of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd againſt Idolatry, he was mightily concern'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, <hi>and rent his Cloaths;</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 11.</note> he conſider'd himſelf as obnoxious to the Threatning as his People, and therefore commanded
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52511:10"/> Prieſts and Princes <hi>to go and enquire of the Lord for him and his People,</hi>
               <note place="margin">12. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and for all Judah, about it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>He ſent and gathered together all the Elders of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah and Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 34.29, 30.</note> 
               <hi>and the Prieſts and the Levites, and all the People great and ſmall, and went up into the Houſe of the Lord, and read the Book of the Covenant unto them:</hi> that they might all be made ſenſible of the grievous ſin of Idolatry, and the Wrath of the Lord againſt it, and might be moved thereby to repent of it, and renounce it.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, He and the People made a <hi>Solemn Covenant</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord,<note place="margin">2 Kings 23.3.</note> 
               <hi>to walk after the Lord, and to keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and his Teſtimonies, and his Statutes, with all their heart, and all their Soul, to perform the words of the Covenant, that were written in the Book of the Law.</hi> Herein, the King and his Subjects prov'd themſelves to be Religious indeed, for all True Religion is an entring into <hi>Solemn League and Covenant with God,</hi> to be true to him and his Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>The terms, <hi>League, Covenant, Aſſociation,</hi> have a brand of Infamy put upon them by ſome men, whoſe Ears are grated at the ſound, and their Stomachs raiſed at the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them; they are as great pretenders to Knowledge as any men we diſcourſe with, and yet as blind and ignorant as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> their Forefathers: for as they boaſted of their being the <hi>Seed of Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 8.33. — 9.28.</note> and <hi>Diſciples of Moſes,</hi> but <hi>erred</hi> not <hi>knowing the Scriptures:</hi> So our Modern Phariſees talk much of their being the <hi>True Sons of the Church,</hi> and <hi>Lovers of the Common-Prayer,</hi> when they are, many of them, as ignorant as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, in points of Real ſaving Knowledge, and underſtand no Covenanting with God, but that Popiſh, Childiſh, perfunctory and unwarrantable one, of Godfathers and Godmothers for them in their Infancy, which when they come to Age, they are uſually as careleſs altogether to perform, as their Subſtitutes did at firſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently and ſuperſtitiouſly engage. But thus it happens among all Ways of Religion (thô never ſo highly applauded by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionary Profeſſors) which are deſtitute of Divine Authority.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:52511:10"/>
            <p>Fifthly, He and his People having taken the <hi>Covenant, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> to walk after the Lord, and to keep his Commandments,</hi> &amp;c. there was no delay, no fear of precipitation, and waiting for a more convenient Seaſon, which are too often ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to Religious Princes by carnal Counſellors; but down went the <hi>High places, Groves, Altars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 34. &amp; 2. Kings 23.</note> 
               <hi>Prieſts of Baal</hi> immediately: And ſo univerſal was the Reformation, that not one publick Monument of Idolatry was ſpared through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, He reſtored the Paſſeover to its right Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> commanding it to be kept exactly according to what was written <hi>in the Book of the Covenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 23.21 v. 22.</note> from which he turned not aſide, by putting to, or taking from. Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the celebration of this Feaſt, it is recorded, <hi>Surely there was not holden ſuch a Paſſeover, from the days of Samuel the Prophet, nor in all the days of the Kings of Iſrael, nor of the Kings of Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seventhly, He took care that no Publick Idolatry ſhould be practiſed in his days, whatſoever ſome of the Prieſts and People did privately; for 'tis ſaid,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 34 33.</note> 
               <hi>he made them ſerve the Lord their God. And all his days they departed not from following the Lord, the God of their Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon conſideration now of the whole matter it might well be recorded of <hi>Joſiah,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Like unto him was there no King before him, that turned to the Lord with all his heart, and with all his ſoul, and with all his might, according to all the Law of Moſes, neither after him aroſe there any like him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words theſe three things are preſented to our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations:</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s perſonal Eminency above all other Kings, <hi>Like unto him was there no King before him,</hi> &amp;c. Which is to be taken as in the Inſtances above mentioned, and thô it includes his publick and private Deportment, yet it ſeems moſtly to relate to his extraordinary Zeal for God in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Reformation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Subject matter of his matchleſs Glory,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52511:11"/> namely, his own Converſion, and his Peoples Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; wherein his Love to God was very conſpicuous, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we conſider its Integrity or Extent; for it was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſincere, but univerſal alſo; <hi>he turned to the Lord with all his heart, and with all his ſoul, and with all his might.</hi> He was not almoſt, but altogether a Convert; he had not a double Heart, one for God, and another for <hi>Baal,</hi> dividing himſelf between true and Idolatrous Worſhip; No, <hi>he turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Lord with all his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Rule he walked by in rooting out Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and reſtoring the pure Worſhip of God, not the High Prieſts Decretalls, or the Canons of the Clergy, or the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary Acts of the <hi>Sanhedrin;</hi> but the <hi>Law of Moſes;</hi> according to which he ſtrictly acted in all his Proceedings about the Reformation.</p>
            <p>The Doctrinal Obſervations from hence are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, Thoſe Princes are only Eminent in the ſight of God, who are truly Religious, and <hi>turn to the Lord with all their heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, There is more required of ſuch Princes, than their own private Aſſent and Conſent to the true Religion; they muſt promote it in their Dominions, by all ſuch ways as are commanded or allow'd of in Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, They cannot be capable of a greater Honour in this World, than to be the Inſtruments of a Godly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation among their Subjects.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, The Word of God alone is the Rule, to which both they and their People muſt attend in all matters rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Religion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thoſe Princes are only Eminent in the ſight of God, who are truly Religious, and <hi>turn to the Lord with all their heart.</hi> For ſuch are Vines of his own planting, Kings ſet up by him to <hi>Rule in the fear of God,</hi> they are his Darlings and Favourites: Not that they can do any thing of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, how Great and Potent ſoever they be, to merit, or any way procure the Divine Favour and Protection; their very Exaltation to their Thrones being an Act of pure Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficence.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52511:11"/> But they are eminent in his Eſtimation, upon the account of thoſe Graces, which ſpring from the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt, and do manifeſt themſelves in an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate Zeal for God. As for thoſe Princes who are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd Enemies of God and Religion, they may be ſaid to be ſet up by God too, becauſe <hi>All Power is of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> But then we muſt remember what God himſelf ſays of ſuch, He <hi>gives them</hi> to a People <hi>in his Anger;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 13.11.</note> and conſider in what ſence they are conſtituted by him, <hi>ut flagella Dei,</hi> as the Scourge to puniſh the Rebellions of a Nation. So that the <hi>Powers that be</hi> in the World, whether Good or Bad, are <hi>ordained of God;</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Bad Princes are Gods Ordinance of Wrath and Permiſſion, Good Princes of ſpecial Love, Choice and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation. The firſt are given in his Diſpleaſure, the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his Good will to a People.</p>
            <p>There is much Controverſie among the Learned about the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ham. Annot. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loc. Chryſtoſt. &amp; Theophil. in lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sherlocks <hi>Caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Alleg.</hi> Baxters <hi>Annot</hi> Clarks <hi>Annot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> and therefore muſt not paſs without a little Examination. Some take it for the perſon inveſted with the Power of Government; others for the Office of the Prince, not his Perſon; ſome underſtand all manner of Power right or wrong, if it gets the Poſſeſſion, and have the Adminiſtration of Affairs. Others underſtand Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Right to Govern, obſerving a Criticiſm between <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſome think will not bear the Teſt. And others comprehend both lawful Authority, and the Perſons exerciſing it: But whether we take it for Legal Authority, or uſurped, for the Perſon or the Office of the Prince, or for both; the thing is much the ſame, for Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity it ſelf is certainly Gods Ordinance,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the perſons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing it, are placed ſo by his permiſſive or Effective Providence.</p>
            <p>How far the People are intereſted in placing or diſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the Supream Magiſtrate, and whether he be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to the whole Community, thô ſuperiour to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuals, are improper Enquiries, when the Government is ſettled in Excellent hands, and Liberty and Property ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured. I ſhall only mind you of Gods ſpecial Deſignation
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52511:12"/> upon ſome Perſons, and the turning of the Peoples Hearts unto them, after a moſt wonderful manner, and his mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Abdication of others, as utterly unfit to Govern, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Blaſt upon all their Attempts, while the others Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes are bleſt with an unaccountable Succeſs; and again, that the people have ſometimes a mighty ſtroke under Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in the Diſpoſal of Crowns, and at other times they ſtand amazed to behold their Unconcernedneſs in the Revolutions of the World.</p>
            <p>There is an Objection to one part of this Diſcourſe, that if <hi>all Power be of God,</hi> and <hi>the Powers that be</hi> are of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, how doth he then complain in <hi>Hoſea? They have ſet up Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ch. 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>but not of me; they have made Princes, and I knew it not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, that <hi>All Power is of God</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and Government is his Ordinance, although the people ſet up Wicked Kings, and make Princes, ſuch as <hi>he knows not,</hi> that is, approves not. His permiſſive Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence tolerates, what his Effective Providence allows not. We muſt therefore diſtinguiſh between Soveraign Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the manner of acquiring and adminiſtring of the ſame.<note place="margin">John 19.11.</note> Authority it ſelf, or Power to Govern, is from God; but yet the Throne may be aſcended by unlawful ſteps, or being lawfully mounted, it may be filled with Apoſtacy, Cruelty, and Violence; and ſo the Perſon ſitting thereon may be diſowned by God, as a Tyrant or Uſurper.</p>
            <p>Or thus it may be anſwered, this place in <hi>Hoſea</hi> reſpects the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> revolt from <hi>Rehoboam</hi> to <hi>Jeroboam;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Kings 14.7, 8.</note> and if we weigh the thing well, the Tranſlation of the Kingdom was from God, and ſo <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was a King of Gods ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up, and the People did their Duty in transferring their Allegiance to him: But his falling away immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after he was made King from the true Worſhip of God, to that of the <hi>Golden Calves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Kings 12.28, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 30.14.9, 16.</note> which he had ſet up in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and cauſing the People to ſin therewith, was from the Devil, and ſo God renounces him.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:52511:12"/>
            <p>But thô the Authority of Kings (generally ſpeaking) be of God, and the Bad too often make a greater Figure in the World than the Good; yet the Good are his choice, his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Ones, who with <hi>Joſiah</hi> are truly Religious, <hi>and turn to the Lord with all their heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how may poor revolted Mortals be ſaid to turn to God, have they any Power to turn themſelves before they are turned?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, No; they have not in their Natural, Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed State any more Power to turn themſelves ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God, than the <hi>Ethiopian has to change his skin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 13.23.</note> 
               <hi>or the Leopard his ſpots.</hi> God muſt firſt turn to them before they can turn to him; yea, he muſt <hi>turn them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—31.18.</note> or they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>be turned,</hi> for no leſs Power than Omnipotence can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert a Soul. But when the Soul is effectually converted, then it will turn to, and claſp about God. The motions of converted Souls towards God, are like the turnings of the Needle touched with a Load-ſtone to the North; for being touched with the Magnet of his Love, they draw inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly towards him. In ſuch Souls the Attraction of Free-Grace is ſo ſtrong, that nothing can poſſibly prevent it. The Saints are ſenſible of great ſlackneſs and backwardneſs in their Spiritual progreſs, of many ſtops and hinderances in their Chriſtian Race, but they are ſecured againſt total and final Apoſtacy, by Gods everlaſting Covenant of Free-Grace, ſealed and ratified in the Blood of Chriſt, by many ſweet and precious promiſes to keep them from falling away, by vertue of their Myſtical Union with Chriſt, and the Prayer and Interceſſion of Chriſt for them: They meet with many Aſſaults from Sin, Satan, and the World; but Sin cannot ſeparate them from the Love of God in Chriſt, becauſe that is pardoned in the Blood of Chriſt; Satan cannot vanquiſh them, becauſe Chriſt hath ſubdued him; and the World cannot overcome them, becauſe Chriſt hath overcome the World. But thô the Saints are ſecured from all danger of final and total Apoſtacy, yet this is no ground of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs and carnal Confidence to them; the way of their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52511:13"/> Salvation is of Gods own ordering and appointing, and it is this,<note place="margin">Pet. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>They are Elect according to the fore-knowledge of God the Father, through Sanctification of the Spirit unto Obedience, and ſprinkling of the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Mark this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, <hi>Through Sanctification of the Spirit unto Obedience;</hi> they are not Elected to Salvation without the Spirits Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto Obedience, but they are Elected to attain Salvation by Sanctification as the means to the End: and being ſanctified by the Spirit of God, they are thereby enabled to perform Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Goſpel. God did not Elect them that they ſhould be careleſs,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ph. 1.4.</note> but that they ſhould be carefull; for they are <hi>choſen of him in Chriſt before the foundation of the World, that they ſhould be holy, and without blame before him in love.</hi> They are choſen to the Means, and the diligent uſe thereof, as well as to the End:<note place="margin">h. 2.10.</note> For <hi>they are Gods Workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, which God hath before ordained, that they ſhould walk in them.</hi> This denotes their Courſe, 'tis a <hi>walking in good works;</hi> they are Elected to live in the conſtant exerciſe of all Graces infuſed into them, and of all Duties required of them. They then moſt horridly abuſe the precious Doctrine of the Saints Perſeverance, who call it a Doctrine of Looſeneſs and Libertiniſm, and pretend it takes away all Watchfulneſs and Diligence in Duty; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it requires all poſſible ſtrictneſs and exactneſs from the Saints. And certainly no perſons in the World can conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves under ſtronger tyes to Obedience, than they who believe that 'tis Gods method in their Salvation to bring them to it of Free Grace, through Sanctification of the Spirit unto Obedience, and Sprinkling of the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt. For believing this to be Gods Way of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they will endeavour to be found in it; and knowing that <hi>God hath choſen them to Salvation through Sanctification of the Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſ. 2.13, 15, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and belief of the Truth;</hi> they will pray that they may <hi>ſtand fast, and have their hearts comforted and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in every good word and work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this Score it is, namely, Election in Chriſt, and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the Spirit, that Princes become truly Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52511:13"/> and ſo highly eminent in the ſight of God; and by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue thereof their Dominions are founded in Grace, and have a Spiritual ſuperadded to their Political Right. I do not ſay, that the Godly or Gracious only have a Political Right to Govern, but that Gracious Princes have a double one; Firſt, As Princes, and Secondly, much more (I am ſure much better) as being gracious Princes. By how much the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Spirit excells that of the Body, by ſo much the Scepter poliſhed with Grace outſhines its Native luſtre.</p>
            <p>Impious Rulers are compared by <hi>Solomon</hi> to <hi>roaring Lyons and ranging Bears,</hi> the moſt ſavage Beaſts of prey,<note place="margin">Prov. 28.15.</note> to ſet forth their Violence, Cruelty and Oppreſſion. Lyons and Bears, the Naturaliſts tell us, are naturally crueller than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wild Creatures, but <hi>when pinch'd with hunger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sed cum fame premuntur ſeipſos crudelitate ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</note> 
               <hi>they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the cruelty of their Natures.</hi> In thoſe Creatures we have a lively portraicture of Arbitrary and Tyrannical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,, who as cruelly prey upon the <hi>poor</hi> oppreſſed <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> as they do upon the Beaſts of the Field.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tenui populo</hi> Ar. Mont. Rom. 13.3, 4.</note> With a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle variation of the Apoſtles words, we may ſay of them, They are a <hi>terror to good works, and Revengers to execute wrath upon them that do well.</hi> They are Perverters of publick peace and Order, and men have no Security, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Law, of Life or Property under them: For they care not what ravage and ſpoil they make of their Counrrey, vainly fancying the people are made for them, not they made for the People; contrary to what <hi>Seneca</hi> writes to <hi>Nero, That the Commonwealth is not theirs to uſe as they liſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Non Republicam ſuam eſſe ſed ſe Republicae. de <hi>Clem. l. 1. c. 19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>but they are the Commonwealth's.</hi> Which makes me ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed when I read or hear what unſuitable Titles ſome <hi>Parazites</hi> give them, and how <hi>Jeroboam's, Herods, Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines, Diocleſians,</hi> and <hi>Julians,</hi> Idolaters, Adulterers, bloody Perſecutors, and infamous Apoſtates, are complemented with the glorious Appellations of the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sen. Epiſt.</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Q. Curt. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of God, as the Heathen Prieſts flattered <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and perſwaded him to be <hi>Jupiters Son,</hi> thô King <hi>Philip</hi> was his Father.</p>
            <p>But as Wicked Rulers are like <hi>roaring Lyons, and ranging
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52511:14"/> Bears;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 49.23.</note> ſo Religious Kings and Queens are compared to <hi>Nurſing Fathers and Nurſing Mothers.</hi> The Glory of God, and Welfare of their People ſway more with ſuch, than their own ſelf-Intereſt, or Perſonal Greatneſs. They always poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone their private Advantages to the publick Good, and make leſs reckoning of their own than their Subjects ſafety. And this is notorious, from thoſe many dangers they voluntarily expoſe themſelves to, which 'tis not imaginable they would ever do, if they had not more regard to the Honour of God and the Subjects Weal, than to their own Applauſe and Intereſts.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtories inform us of ſome that ſacrificed their Lives upon their Countries ſcore, as <hi>Codrus, Decius,</hi> and ſeveral others; but whence ſprang this adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous Love? from natural Courage, Ambition, vain Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Affectation of a Statue, ſuperſtitious obſervation of Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, or the like. But truly Religious Princes act from No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler Principles, and are moved by the mighty impulſe of him, <hi>who ſits upon the Circle of the Earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 40.22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>and the Inhabitants thereof are as Graſhoppers; that bringeth Wicked Princes to nothing, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Judges of the Earth as Vanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now who thoſe Princes be that are truly Religious, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many pretenders are in the World, is not very eaſie for us to know. The Heart falls not within our Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, for no man can ſufficiently underſtand his own, and how then ſhould he know another Mans? we leave that therefore to his Judgment, who is the Maker and Searcher of it.</p>
            <p>The Text deſcribes them to us by an univerſal Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Law of God, <hi>in turning to him with all their heart, with all their Soul, and with all their might:</hi> which ſhews the nature of true Converſion, it muſt be Univerſal. A partial Change is an imperfect one; for half an Heart is ſuch an Offering as God will have no reſpect unto. He who made the whole, requires the whole; and therefore he who gives him not the whole, but reſerves a part for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52511:14"/> robs God of his Right, and by that reſervation deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately cheats himſelf too.</p>
            <p>Our exacteſt Scrutinies cannot penetrate any further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Heart of Man, becauſe it lyes quite out of our ſight, than it diſcovers it ſelf by Overt Acts. This we know, an Hypocrite may for a time appear to be a Saint, but his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor will off at one time or other; for <hi>will he delight himſelf in the Almighty? will he always call upon God?</hi> Job 27.10. But where there is true Grace in the Heart, there will not be a Perſonating, but a real Acting of Holineſs in the Life: Can the Fountain be ſweet, and yet ſend forth bitter ſtreams? Can the Tree be good, and not the Fruit? So it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a Sanctified Heart not to ſhew it ſelf in a Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Life. In whomſoever the principle of true Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is rooted, it will ſpread and branch out it ſelf, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to others. Holineſs is not only of a Diffuſive, but alſo of an Aſſimilating Nature, and would have all like it ſelf. When men are throughly converted, they will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the Converſion of others. Having effectually taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the immerited Love of God, they will be telling what he hath done for their Souls; and having their Hearts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed with the fragrancy of Free-Grace, they will always retain the Scent, and be ever admiring and commending it to others.</p>
            <p>We may then ſay, that truly Religious Princes will not put their Candle under a Buſhel, but ſet it in a Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, that it may give light to their Subjects; nor hide their precious Oyntment, but break the Box of Spikenard, that the Odour may perfume the People: For they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Obligation to countenance and encourage the Goſpel, and to endeavour the Reformation of thoſe under them. For,</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is more required of ſuch Princes, than <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> their own private Aſſent and Conſent to the true Religion; they muſt promate it in their Dominions, by all ſuch ways as are allowed or commanded of in Scripture. It is the Duty of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian to do what he can for God, and the Kingdom of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52511:15"/> his Son, in his private Capacity; and then much more the Prince's, who is exalted to an higher ſtation, and placed in an Orb, wherein he may ſhine as the Sun before his people. It is no part of my preſent work to ſpeak of the power of Princes in matters Civil and Political, the Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Government muſt be the Rule there:<note n="*" place="margin">Defence of the Preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</note> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">We muſt have recourſe to the wholſome Laws and Cuſtoms of our Countrey, for our direction in Civil Proceedings. Neither our Saviour, nor his Apoſtles intermeddled with Civil Government, but left that as they found it. <hi>Chriſts</hi> Kingdom was not of this World, and therefore he and his Apoſtles medled no farther with the Kingdoms of the World, than to teach all their Duties in their reſpective Stations, the Magiſtrates to Rule, and the people to Obey in the fear of God. The Standard of our Civil Government is the Law of the Land; it is ſuperiour to all Orders and Ranks of Men, and looks with an equal aſpect upon the Prince and People.</q> The Author of <hi>Jovian</hi> ſays, that the <hi>King is a Soveraign doubly limited,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 212.</note> 
               <hi>by the Laws of God, and the Civil Laws of his Kingdom.</hi> And (out of <hi>Bracton</hi>) adds, <hi>Et ſub Lege,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>quia Lex facit Regem:</hi> He is under the Law, becauſe the Law makes the King. And Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> upon the words,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pract. latech.</hi> l. 2. p. 160.</note> 
               <hi>[He beareth not the Sword in vain, he is God's Miniſter, an Avenger for wrath to him that doth ill]</hi> ſays, By this <hi>is intimated, that the Sword is, as far as reſpects this Life, put into the hands of the lawful Magiſtrate, with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to uſe it, as the Conſtitution of the Kingdom ſhall beſt direct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore limit my Diſcourſe to things pertaining to Religion, and enquire briefly how far the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is intereſted therein; and this I ſhall do with humble reverence to Almighty God, and a due reſpect to thoſe whom he hath ſet over us in the Government of this Realm, by laying down a few Theſes or Poſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt is the Supream Head, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.23. Col. 2.10.</note> and Legiſlator of his Church, and he hath not dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52511:15"/> this his Headſhip, Government, and Legiſlature,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.18, 19, 20. Joh. 15.14. Jam. 4.12. Iſai. 9.6, 7.</note> to any Perſon, or Perſons upon Earth. He hath left no Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Vicar or Deputy to preſide over it; for neither Pope, nor general Councils, nor National Synods, nor the Civil Magiſtrate ſingly, or with the Body Repreſentative in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, have any Soveraign Authority in Church Affairs. In things purely Divine they cannot make one Law to bind the Conſcience to Obedience. They have nothing to do to make Articles of Faith, to compoſe Forms of Prayer and Worſhip, and impoſe them upon the people under Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, to make Eccleſiaſtical Canons and Rubricks, and to decree Rites and Ceremonies. Chriſt hath ſtrictly tyed his Church to the obſervation of the Rules laid down by him in his Word: <hi>Ye are my Friends if ye do whatſoever I command you,</hi> John 15.14. I your ſole Lord, Head, and Maſter, to whom <hi>all Power in Heaven and Earth is given,</hi> Mat. 28.18. And therefore the Churches of Chriſt own none other Head but him; nay, they dare not own any other, becauſe <hi>God hath put all things under his feet, and given him to be the Head over all things to the Church,</hi> Eph. 1.22. To admit of any other Head, whether Polilical or Miniſterial, were to deny his Headſhip. The Saints are the beſt friends to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> they are, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaid of <hi>Elijah, The Chariot of Iſrrel, and the Horſmen thereof,</hi> 2 Kings 2.12. But they are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Gods.</hi> With reſpect to things Civil, they will, yea, they muſt own the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magiſtrate; but with reſpect to Divine Worſhip, they muſt own no Maſter or Superior but Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Argument that the Sticklers for Magiſtratical Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in Religion draw from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Kings, is of no force under the Diſpenſation of the Goſpel, could they prove what they are never able to do, that they were<note n="*" place="margin">God was its a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone Head, the Government being a Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy. <hi>Jerubbaal.</hi> p. 312.</note> Heads of the Church: becauſe, as the Learned <hi>Anſwerer</hi> of Mr. <hi>Tomb</hi>'s <hi>Theodulia</hi> ſaith, <hi>Betwixt the Oeconomy of the Law and Goſpel, there is a vaſt diſproportion; many things were of old lawful, which now to practiſe were no leſs than a denyal of Chriſt come in the fleſh.</hi> And a little after, the ſame Worthy
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52511:16"/> Author ſays, <hi>That neither the Rulers of the Jews, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations had</hi> de Jure <hi>any ſuch Dominion or Power over their Subjects, as to make Laws, introduce Conſtitutions of their own framing, in Matters relating to Worſhip, and compell them by force and Violence to be ſubject thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As little ſucceſs they have had, who urge the Power aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by the firſt Chriſtian <hi>Emperours;</hi> for if they took upon them the Headſhip of the Church, they invaded Chriſts Prerogative; and it is not what they did, but what they had Warrant from the Word to do, that is Preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to us.</p>
            <p>Thoſe <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Kings, <hi>David, Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi> had Divine Warrant for what they did; and <hi>Solomon</hi> in depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Abiathar</hi> from the Prieſthood, acted not as Head of the Church, but as King of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> for as the <hi>Author</hi> before mention'd truly diſtinguiſheth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerubbaal</hi> p. 314</note> 
               <hi>Solomon depoſed Abiathar not as High Pontifee, or Head of the Church, for Male adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Church Affairs, but as King of Iſrael, for treaſon againſt the Commonwealth, in the buſineſs of Adonijah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though Chriſt hath conſtituted no Heads, Vicars, or Deputies over his Churches, yet he hath not left them without a Power to act by in Church Society: For, when people by the inward working of the Spirit, through the outward Miniſtry of the Word, are effectually wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and have voluntarily joyn'd themſelves into Church Fellowſhip, for the mutual participation of all the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, they have then a power to Elect ſuch Perſons as they ſhall judge fitted with Spiritual Gifts and Qualifications for the Miniſtry and Exerciſe of the ſame Power, and therein they are to proceed by a cloſe adherence to the Rule of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>To prevent all Miſtakes touching the Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which Chriſt hath given to his Church, I do not aſſert any <q rend="margQuotes">Soveraign,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>wen</hi>'s true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ature of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>el Ch. c. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 163.</note> Legiſlative or Lordly Power, but ſuch as is Declarative or Miniſterial, only with reſpect to Chriſts Authority, and the Churches Liberty, and in it's
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52511:16"/> nature is purely Spiritual; for whether we conſider the Object, the Souls and Conſciences of Men; or the End, the Glory of God, in directing of them to live unto God, and to come to the fruition of him; or the Rule, the Word and Command of Chriſt himſelf alone; or the Acts and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of it, in Binding and Looſing, in Remitting and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Sin, in opening and ſhutting the Kingdom of Heaven; it is in every part meerly and only ſpiritual: From whence the Concluſion is plain, that all ſuch Acts and Exerciſe of Rule or Government, from any Intereſt in Church Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, which are Carnal, Political, Deſpotical, of Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Operation, or not entirely Spiritual, are utterly to be excluded, as wholly Heterogeneous to Chriſts Headſhip and Government.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Churches of Chriſt are not National or Political Bodies,<note place="margin">See <hi>Aſſembly</hi> in their <hi>Jus Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vinum, Ruther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ford</hi> in his Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vine Right of Ch. Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> as States and Commonwealths, but they are Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Spiritual Societies, and have Laws and Offices di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from thoſe of the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) They have Laws formally different from thoſe of the Commonwealth, <hi>viz.</hi> The Precepts of Chriſt himſelf alone: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. About Church Officers, they muſt have a Divine Call and Miſſion, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. and <hi>John</hi> 20.21.</p>
            <p n="2">2. About Church Duties, as Prayer, Preaching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which muſt all be performed according to the Word.</p>
            <p n="3">3. About Church gathering and Diſcipline; Members are to be admitted, and Offendors dealt with as the Rule, the Command of Chriſt directs.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The Churches of Chriſt have Officers diſtinct from thoſe of the Civil Magiſtrate, they are of his ſending and appointment, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.8.11. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28; they are elected and ordained by the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3, 4, and 14, 23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. and <hi>Acts</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 4; they act in Chriſt's
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52511:17"/> Name, and by his Authority, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20.</p>
            <p>It is the ſaying of <hi>Optatus Milevitanus</hi> an <hi>African</hi> Biſhop,<note n="†" place="margin">Non enim Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publica eſt in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia; ſed Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Republi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>câ. <hi>Lib. 3.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>the Commonwealth is not in the Church, but the Church is in the Commonwealth.</hi> And 'tis a great Truth, for were it otherwiſe, the two Societies would be confounded, which are eſſentially diſtinct from each other. If the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth ſhould be in the Church, then there could be no Church but there muſt alſo be a Commonwealth, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever there is a Commonwealth, there would be a Church. But this is ſo abſurd, I will not ſpend time in the confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it. We learn from the Word, that the Churches of Chriſt are gathered out of the Kingdoms and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths of the World, by the preaching of the Goſpel, and united into Bodies by other Bonds and Confederations than Civil Societies are; the Members of the one may be Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the other Society, but the Laws, Officers and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Adminiſtration are perfectly diſtinct.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Civil Magiſtrate has no Legiſlative or Coercive power in things of meer Religion. 'Tis his duty to protect the Churches of Chriſt in the free Exerciſe of Religious Worſhip, to puniſh Vice and Prophaneneſs, and to miniſter Juſtice to Evil doers. But he has no power to <hi>inſtitute, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, change</hi> or <hi>aboliſh</hi> any thing in the Worſhip of God, or to puniſh the man for his Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Civil Magiſtrate is to Rule his Subjects in the fear of God, and to be a Nurſing Father to the Churches of Chriſt. He ought to be a perſon as <hi>David</hi> was, <hi>a man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods own Heart;</hi> a Man Exemplary for Holineſs, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and all other Vertues, and to promote, as much as in him lyes, by Precept, Recommendation, and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, true Piety and Religion in their Dominions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, Religious Princes cannot be capable of a greater Honour in this World, than to be the Inſtruments of a Godly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52511:17"/> Reformation among their Subjects. Some Princes have been bloody Murtherers of their Countrey, and cruel Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors of their people, and have made Laws for the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of their Barbarities:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Aug.</hi> tom 4.</note> Thus <hi>Valerian</hi> enacted againſt the poor Chriſtians, That <hi>unleſs they ſacrificed to the Heathen Gods, they ſhould be expoſed to divers kinds of Puniſhments;</hi> and <hi>Diocleſians</hi> Edict againſt them was, <hi>That no Man ſhould ſell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beda</hi> in <hi>hymno</hi> Jul. Mart.</note> 
               <hi>or ſecretly give them any thing, except they would firſt burn In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to the Gods.</hi> Theſe and all like them ſhall ſtink for ever in the infamy of their Names, whiles the memories of good Princes ſhall be always precious. The remembrance of the one ſhall rot, and the other ſhall be ever freſh and flouriſhing. The remembrance of <hi>Joſiah</hi> is like the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume that is made by the Art of the Apothecary; it is as ſweet as Honey in all Mouths, and as Muſick at a Banquet of Wine: He behaved himſelf uprightly in the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the People, and took away all the abominations of Iniquity: He directed his Heart unro the Lord, and in the time of the Ungodly he eſtabliſh'd Religion. <hi>Jeroboam, Omri, Ahab,</hi> and other wicked and irreligious Kings, have left a Brand of Ignominy upon their Names, that time will never wear out. The decree of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3.29. Dan. 6.26. Ezra 1.1, 2,</note> for ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing honourably of the God of <hi>Shadrach, Meſhech</hi> and <hi>Abedne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go;</hi> of <hi>Darius,</hi> for worſhipping the God of <hi>Daniel;</hi> and of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> for building the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> more beautifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Diadem's, than all their Victories and Empire over Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Emperour that embraced the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, was ſurnamed <hi>the Great,</hi> more for his Piety than his Greatneſs. 'Tis the protecting, favouring, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging of Religion, that brings in the largeſt Revenues of Glory to Princes. Such ſhall have the Divine Protection to watch over them, for <hi>the eye of the Lord is over them that fear him, and put their hope in his mercy,</hi> Pſal. 33.18. They ſhall conſtantly be remembred in the prayers of the Lords People, and have a Name more honourable and laſting, than one cut in Beams of Cedar, or Pillars of Braſs.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52511:18"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>2</label> Fourthly, The Word of God alone is the Rule to which both Princes and People muſt attend in all matters relating to Religion. Whoever ſhall go about to redreſs the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, will undertake an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Work undoubtedly, acceptable to God, and deſired by all good Men; and my earneſt prayers ſhall be, that he may never fail of ſucceſs in ſo brave and Chriſtian an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize. The meaſures that ſome Princes have obſerved, have been taken from wrong Standards, carnal Ends, and worldly Counſels; and they themſelves have been rather governed by Schemes and platforms of deſigning Men, than the unerring Oracles of the Living God, which doubtleſs has been one main <hi>Remora</hi> to a thorough Reformation. It was this which ſtifled the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reformation in the Birth, and if not removed, will render all attempts of this kind abortive. For whiles men adviſe a Reformation ſuitable to ſuch Models as they themſelves contrive, and refuſe to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the Lord Chriſt commanding and directing in his Word? what ought to be done, how can it be expected that ever a good End ſhould be attained, when the only adequate means are omitted? When the Affairs of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are as carnally debated as Temporal matters, and the Church is no otherwiſe conſidered than as a part of the State; nay, when things are ſo jumbled, that there is no diſcerning Church from State, but perſons are made Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the former, as ſoon as they are born Subjects of the latter, and ſo come to know hardly any other Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than what they are told they received by <hi>Infant-Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:</hi> in a word, when nothing will content ſome Men but a Draught of Reformation forg'd in the Shop of their own Brains, or when they are ſo ſtubborn that they will not ſubmit to the Inclination of an Excellent Prince, or ſo blind, that they cannot ſee the neceſſity of an Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; we may as ſoon hope to ſee <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> turn <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> as ſome <hi>Vizarded Proteſtants</hi> ſet forward a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: For Reformation work is contrary to the ſenſual
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52511:18"/> Luſts and Intereſts of worldly men, and therefore will meet with conſtant oppoſition from them; yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their endeavours to obſtruct it, nothing ſhall be able to ſtand before him whom God hath appointed to the Work. All difficulties ſhall be removed, and hinderances immediately vaniſh in that day, that the Lord ſhall ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>Zerubbabel, Not by might, nor by power,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 4.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>but by my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts: Who art thou, O great Mountain? before Zerubbabel thou ſhalt become a plain, and he ſhall bring forth the Head-ſtone thereof, with ſhoutings, crying Grace, Grace, unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, <hi>Be ſtrong O Zerubbabel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hag. 2.4. 1 Chron. 12.32. Hag. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and be ſtrong all ye people, who have underſtanding of the times to know what Iſrael ought to do, for I am with you ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for thoſe Dignitaries of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a willingneſs to reform Errors and Abuſes, by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Canons and Conſtitutions; I humbly deſire them to conſider whether mens Traditions are a good Rule to reform by, becauſe they are erroneous; and whether the Word of God is not a ſufficient Rule of it ſelf, without their ſinful Additions? Let the Sacred <hi>Book</hi> therefore be opened, and if upon examination the Building be <hi>Babel,</hi> let it be pull'd down, and not one ſtone left upon another, how goodly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Structure hath been in the Eyes of the long dazled and deluded Spectators.</p>
            <p>Conſult no longer with the baſe Inclinations, and corrupt reaſonings of Fleſh and Blood; but away to the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Teſtimony;</hi> Covenant with the Lord, as <hi>Joſiah</hi> and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did, <hi>to keep his Commandments and his Teſtimonies with all your heart, and with all your ſoul,</hi> 2 Chron. 34.31.</p>
            <p>And whereas there are ſome others that would perſwade the People, that no Reformation is needful, I would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them ſeriouſly to anſwer me theſe following Queſtions:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Was a Reformation neceſſary in <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s time, and did he well in reſtoring the true Worſhip of God? Is the Caſe of <hi>England</hi> much different from that of <hi>Judah</hi>'s? Nay, is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52511:19"/> not our Apoſtacy as palpable as hers? and then are not we in as much need of a Reformation?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are the <hi>Cathedral</hi> and <hi>Parochial</hi> Churches (as they are vulgarly called) of <hi>England,</hi> called and conſtituted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rule and Order of the Goſpel, or are they not? if they are not, then they cannot but ſtand, in need of Reformation: If they are, then theſe two things (among others) muſt be made out:
<list>
                  <item>1. That they have the right <hi>Matter,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>2. The right <hi>Form</hi> of a Goſpel-Church.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. If they have the right Matter of a Goſpel Church, then the Perſons or Members thereof are Viſible Saints: For by Matter, we underſtand the Perſons whereof a Church conſiſts, with their Qualifications. Now that we may know whether the Members conſtituting the <hi>Cathedral</hi> and <hi>Parochial Churches</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> are Perſons fitly qualified, and ſo right Matter of a Goſpel Church, we will ſee what the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſays in that point, for that muſt be our Rule herein: And upon ſearch we ſhall find the right Matter of a Goſpel-Church to be Viſible Saints; they are called <hi>New Creatures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.17. Heb. 3.1, 1. 1 Pet. 2.5, 9. Joh. 15, 18, 19. Eph. 1.14. 2 Cor. 6.18.</note> 
               <hi>Holy Brethren, Partakers of the Heavenly Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Living ſtones, a choſen Generation, a Royal Prieſthood, an holy Nation, a peculiar people, choſen out of the World, Chriſts purchaſed Poſſeſſion, the Sons and Daughters of the Lord God Almighty.</hi> Now if we can find ſuch a choice, ſelect, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and ſeparate People from the World, that is, from the ſinful Doctrines, Courſes, Cuſtoms, and Society of the World, in the <hi>Cathedral</hi> and <hi>Parochial</hi> Aſſemblies, then they have the right Matter of a Goſpel-Church; if not, but their Members are as mix't as the Head, and the major number openly to be profane, carnal, ſcandalous Livers, ſuch as Swearers, Adulterers, Drunkards, Lyars, Backbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Perſecutors, Revilers, or at beſt meer Formaliſts; have we any ground to call theſe Viſible Saints<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to reckon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52511:19"/> them fit Materials for the Spiritual Building of a Goſpel Church?</p>
            <p n="2">2. As right <hi>Matter,</hi> Viſible Saints are one Conſtituent part of a Goſpel Church, ſo right <hi>Form</hi> is the next thing required to its Eſſence or Being. By Form, I mean, the manner how any Perſons come to be a Church, and that is, by a free Conſent and Agreement to unite in Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, for the performing of all the Duties, and obſervation of all the Appointments of Chriſt, and for the exerciſe of that Power wherewith he hath entruſted them, according to the Rule of his Word. This is the Formal Cauſe or Conſtitutive Form of a particular Church, namely, their<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Owen</hi>'s True Nature of a Goſp. Church, <hi>p.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>Actual, expreſs, voluntary Conſent</hi> to Walk together for the Ends, and according to the Rule aforementioned.</p>
            <p>But you will ask me perhaps: What? is there nothing pre-required unto this Conjunction of Viſible Saints in a particular Church? Is no more to be done, than for Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers immediately to enter into Church Fellowſhip?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, They are firſt to be Baptized, before they are admitted to Church Society. In which point the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſo clear, that there is no place for Heſitation about it. The Church at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was the firſt Goſpel Church, this was <hi>not to depart from thence, but wait for the promiſe of the Father,</hi> Acts 1.4. <hi>The number of the Names was about an hundred and twenty.</hi> v. 15. <hi>Theſe when the day of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt was fully come, were all with one accord in one place,</hi> Acts 2.1. <hi>and were all filled with the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> v. 4. By the help whereof <hi>Peter</hi> proved ſo convincingly to the Murtherers of Chriſt, that <hi>God hath made the ſame Jeſus whom they,</hi> the <hi>Jews, had crucified, both Lord and Chriſt,</hi> v. 36. that <hi>they were pricked in their heart, and ſaid unto Peter, and to the rest of the Apoſtles, Men and Brethren, what ſhall we do?</hi> verſe 37. <hi>Peter</hi> preſently directs them in this their great extremity: <hi>Repent,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and be baptized
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52511:20"/> every one of you in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, for the Remiſſion of Sins, and ye ſhall receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> ver. 38. Upon teſtification of their Faith and Repentance, <hi>they were Baptized about three thouſand Souls,</hi> and <hi>added</hi> to the Church, <hi>v.</hi> 41. Here is a plain Account of the Apoſtles man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of receiving perſons into Church Fellowſhip, <hi>They that gladly received the Word,</hi> were <hi>Baptized,</hi> and then <hi>Added.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If now upon Examination it prove, that ſuch as are Viſible Saints, and <hi>Baptized into Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 6.3. do make up the <hi>Cathedral</hi> and <hi>Parochial</hi> Societies of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> then they are rightly conſtituted in reſpect of <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> and if Mighty Grace having bowed them to the feet of Jeſus, they have freely conſented to give up themſelves to the Lord, and to one another, to walk together in Church Fellowſhip, in obedience to all Chriſts Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then are they alſo rightly conſtituted in reſpect of <hi>Form:</hi> But if one or both of theſe are wanting, as there is cauſe enough to believe ſo: Let them cry, <hi>The Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord are theſe;</hi> and Preach and Print Apologies and Vindications in Defence of the <hi>Excellent Conſtitution,</hi> as they call it, of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> on purpoſe to obſtruct the ſearches of the Inquiſitive, and to retain the Ignorant in their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; this will not juſtifie them before God at the Great Day, thô now their falſe Pleas paſs undiſcovered by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking Croud of poor deluded Wretches.</p>
            <p>I heartily wiſh, that the Guides and Teachers who act by publick Authority, would not be led more by Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt than by Truth; that they would lay down their Prejudices which they imbibed in their Education, and received by Tradition from their Fathers, and would beg of God to direct them to enquire into Goſpel Verities: I am perſwaded the Lord would either teach them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern their Miſtakes, or to exerciſe more Moderation,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52511:20"/> and Charity towards thoſe whoſe Judgments are convinc'd of former Errors.</p>
            <p>I conclude all with a little variation of the Apoſtles words in another caſe,<note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 14.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Let not him</hi> who is in an Error, <hi>judge him</hi> who is convinc'd, <hi>for God hath received him. Who art thou that</hi> cenſureſt and condemneſt another? to Chriſt he ſtandeth in the Truth; <hi>yea, he ſhall be holden up, for God is able to make him ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
